As fans crowded onto the escalator,
their combined weight increased the load
on the main motor, and eventually it hit
a tipping point and the motor started
accelerating uncontrollably.
Safety sensors in the machine noticed
this sudden change and triggered two
things in short succession. First, the
power to the motor was cut, and
immediately after that, the main brake
engaged. Two massive arms clamped down
on the drum to lock it in place and
avert a runaway. This brake should have
had enough stopping power to bring the
fully loaded escalator to a halt even
under the massive strain. [music]
But it didn't. Tests after the incident
showed that its braking force was far
too low, around 37% of the
manufacturer's specification.
The weakened brake struggled to slow the
spinning motor and the escalator's
downhill acceleration continued.
This is when the last line of defense
kicked in.
When the escalator's speed rose by more
than 20%, the auxiliary brake triggered,
driving steel wedges into a disk on the
drive shaft.
But when investigators opened up this
brake, they were shocked. The final
mechanical backstop had been partially
disabled. [music]
Someone had physically tied plastic
straps around one of the two brake
wedges and rendered it useless.